A Guide to the Emil and Betty Hager Collection, American Rhododendron Society
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Emil and Betty Hager Collection American Rhododendron Society
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10553
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Upon the death of Emil and Betty Hager, this material was given to the Special Collections Library, University of Virginia, by Ed Collins, their Power of Attorney, through Sandra McDonald, Hampton, Virginia, on June 24, 2009.
Scope and Content
The Papers of Emil and Betty Hager, 4,700 items (5 Hollinger boxes, 1 Oversize Folder, ca. 2 linear feet), ca. 1948–1998, consists primarily of photographs and slides of people and events connected with the New York Chapter of the American Rhododendron Society. There are also slides of varieties of azaleas and rhododendrons. Also included are slides of vacation trips taken by the couple in Europe, Alaska, Canada, Virginia, U.S. National Parks, and the American West.
Both Emil and Betty Hager were recognized as outstanding hybridizers in the New York Chapter of the American Rhododendron Society. Betty Hager served as the New York Chapter President in 1968–1969 and won the American Rhododendron Society Bronze Medal in 1971.
The slides are grouped topically when a common subject could be determined and any original order retained. Sandra McDonald identified as many of the people and subjects as she could prior to arrangement.
Contents List
- 1965 Certificate of Appreciation - To Betty Hager from New York Chapter of the American Rhododendron Society, as Corresponding Secretary (Box-folder 1:1)
- N.D. Photographs - Miscellaneous Flowers, including: Anna Kehr, Azaleas, Brachycardum, Cibachrome, Clara Raustein, Cynthia, Hybrids, Medusa, Metternichi, Norma, Peggy Ann, Pink Twins, Rustica Flore, Wheatley, White Find, and White Rosebud. (Box-folder 1:2)
- N.D. Photographs - Rhododendrons (Box-folder 1:3)
- 1948–1981 Photographs - Rhododendron People and Groups, including: Awards - Dorothy Schlainier to Jane McKay, Fred Galle to Edmund Mezitt, Bill Tiefjen, Betty Hager, Clara Burns, Edith Griffin, Flower Shows, Franklin West, Fred Rees, George Ring, Hans Bussnik, Jerry Goodman, Laurelwood Gardens - Dorothy Knippenberg, Leslie Tonge, Mal Marum, Mount Mansfield, Opening of Mary Mountford Gift and Garden Shop at Clark Garden - Joseph Guarino, Lemuel Hegwood, John Mountford, Roberta Shavel, and Louisa Spencer, and Planting Fields Arboretum - Emil Hager, Joe Kennedy, Hally McKay, and Pete Sciurba. (Box-folder 1:4)
- 1966–1998 Photographs - Rhododendron People and Groups, including: Al Fuqua, Betty Fuqua, Betty Hager, Betty Hager's Mother, Britt Smith, Clara Burns, Dick Murcott, Edith Griffin, Edmund Mezitt, Emil Hager, Frank Arsen, Fred Galle, Fred Knapp, Fred Rees, Gay Arsen, Gordon Jones, Jane McKay, Jo Hausser, Robert Gartrell, Sid Burns, and Wally McKay. (Box-folder 1:5)
- 1971–1982 Slides - Acadia National Park, including: Bass Harbor, Gardens, Maine Scenery, Mountain Desert, Reid State Park, and South Bubble Erratic (Box-folder 1:6)
- 1975–1986 Slides - Arboretums and Gardens, including: Arsen, Brookgreen, Cape Cod, Clark Memorial Garden, Heritage Plantation, Murcott, National Arboretum, Pilkington Garden, Planting Fields, Raustein, and Robinhill (Box-folder 1:7)
- 1969–1987 Slides - ARS National Chapter Activities, including: Azalea Group Study, Chapter Meetings, Flower Shows, Flower Shows- Potomac Valley Chapter, Gardens, Rhododendron People, and the Valley Forge Convention (Box-folder 1:8)
- 1976–1987 Slides - Azaleas and Rhododendrons, including: Asticou Azalea Garden and Bar Harbor (Box-folder 2:1)
- 1966–1981 Slides - Azaleas and Rhododendrons (Box-folder 2:2)
- 1966–1994 Slides - Azaleas, Rhododendrons, and Various Plants, including: National Arboretum, Phipps Conservatory, and Planting Fields (Box-folder 2:3)
- 1976–1987 Slides - Azaleas, Rhododendrons, and Various Plants, including: Daffodils, Daylilies, and Orchids (Box-folder 2:4)
- 1978–1979 Slides - Bailey Arboretum (Box-folder 2:5)
- 1971–1986 Slides - C.W. Post, Mount Desert, National Arboretum, and National Parks, including: Acadia National Park, Asticou Gardens, Banff National Park, Planting Fields, and Yellowstone (Box-folder 2:6)
- 1964–1986 Slides - Daylilies, including: Daylily Conventions, Seedlings, and Various Plants (Box-folder 2:7)
- 1975–1982 Slides - Family Photos, including: Birthday Party and Snowstorm (Box-folder 2:8)
- 1964–1985 Slides - Flower Shows and Plant Sales, including: Arrington Tour, Gardens, and Garden Shows (Box-folder 3:1)
- 1964–1985 Slides - Flower Shows, including: ARS Truss Show, Coliseum, Planting Fields Center, Roosevelt Fields, and Walt Whitman Mall (Box-folder 3:2)
- 1968–1987 Slides - Flower Shows and Plant Sales, including: ARS Truss Flower Show and National Meetings (Box-folder 3:3)
- 1968–1982 Slides - Gardens, including: Arsen, Dumper, Fuqua, Hager, Herbert Picnic, Kruse Garden, Longwood Conservatory, Phipps, Planting Fields, and the Valley Forge Convention (Box-folder 3:4)
- 1971–1985 Slides - Gardens, including: Flower Shows and People (Box-folder 3:5)
- 1976–1980 Slides - Longwood Gardens, including: Planting Fields (Box-folder 3:6)
- 1962–1979 Slides - National Arboretum, including: Azaleas, New York Chapter Activities, and Various Plants (Box-folder 3:7)
- 1964–1985 Slides - National Chapter Meetings and Rhododendron People (Box-folder 3:8)
- 1967–1978 Slides - Phipps Garden, including: Burns, Murcott, and National Convention (Box-folder 3:9)
- 1968–1979 Slides - Planting Fields Arboretum - Various Plants (Box-folder 4:1)
- 1968–1979 Slides - Planting Fields - Rhododendrons and Scenery (Box-folder 4:2)
- 1960–1983 Slides - Plants and Wildflowers, including: Clematis, Dandelions, Magnolias, Primrose, and Sumac (Box-folder 4:3)
- 1978-198 Slides - Plants - Clark Garden - Roses, Daylilies, and Other Plants (Box-folder 4:4)
- 1964–1986 Slides - Rhododendrons - Garden Tours and Planting Fields (Box-folder 4:5)
- 1968–1977 Slides - Rhododendrons, including: Fall Foliage, Flower Shows, and Rhododendron People (Box-folder 4:6)
- 1969–1976 Slides - Snow and Family Photos, including: Fall Foliage in Snow, Scenery (Box-folder 4:7)
- 1970–1979 Slides - Trips, including: Acadia, Arizona, Canada, Long Island, Montana, Oregon, Skyland, Virginia, Washington, and Williamsburg, Virginia (Box-folder 4:8)
- N.D. Slides - Trips - Alaska and Canada, including: Anchorage, Kotzebue, Skagway, Valdez, and Whitehorse (Box-folder 4:9)
- N.D. Slides - Trips - Austria, Switzerland, Sweden, and Norway, including: Basel (Box-folder 4:10)
- N.D. Slides - Trips - Italy, Niederland, Norway, and Switzerland, including: Davos, Florence, Rome, Siberse, St. Moritz, and Venice (Box-folder 5:1)
- N.D. Slides - Trips - Italy, Spain, and France, including: Barcelona, Madrid, Naples, Paris, and Pisa (Box-folder 5:2)
- N.D. Slides - Trips - Mount Rushmore, including: Canyons and Yosemite (Box-folder 5:3)
- N.D. Slides - Trips - Mount Rushmore and New York, including: Family Photos (Box-folder 5:4)
- N.D. Slides - Trips - New York City and Paris, France (Box-folder 5:5)
- 1960–1994 Slides - Vacation Trips and Various Flowers, including: Bear Mountain, Islip Meadows County Nature Preserve, The Muttontown Preserve, The Sandpoint Preserve, Shenandoah Skyland Drive, and Target Rock National Wildlife Refuge (Box-folder 5:6)
- 1959–1994 Slides - Various Gardens and Plants, including: Azaleas, Dogwood, Raustein Garden, and Satsuki Azaleas (Box-folder 5:7)
- 1972–1980 Slides - Various Plants, including: Bloodroot, Flowers, Herbs, and Rhododendron People, and Snowdrop (Box-folder 5:8)
- 1971–1993 Slides - Various Plants and Personal Photos, including: Artwork, Franklinia, Garden Planting, Hager's Personal Home, Landscapes, Snow, and Queen Anne's lace Oversize Folder (Box-folder 5:9)
- N.D. Flower Prints Natalie Eller & Sharon Defibaugh